Alexander N. Charters Papers
Alexander N. Charters Papers
- Professional correspondence-subject files
  - National Center for Higher Education Management Systems, 1977; report, "A handbook of descriptors of learning opportunities for adults" (Box 133)
  - National Center for the Study of Adult Learning and Literacy (NCSALL), 2002; 2005; printed/promotional material (Box 133)
  - National Coalition for Literacy (NCL), 2008; printed material, including annual report and Literacy Leadership Awards Reception (Box 133)
  - National Community Education Association (NCEA)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 133)
    - Newsletters, 1997-2001; 2 folders (Box 133)
  - National Continuing Education Center for the Health Sciences, See Dean, Larrie.
  - National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education (NCATE), 2005; printed material (Box 133)
  - National Council on Adult Education (NCAE), 1978; 1983; New Zealand; includes copy of annual report (Box 133)
  - National Council of States for the Improvement of Education (NCSIE), based at Nova Southeastern University (Box 133)
  - National Council of States on Inservice Education (NCSIE), 1979; 1989-1990; based at Syracuse University (Box 134)
  - National Education Association (NEA), 1957; 1959,; 1973; roster of attendees at International Adult Education Conference (Box 134)
  - National Education Goals Panel, 1992-1993; annual reports (Box 134)
  - NEA (National Educational Television), See WCNY.
  - National Film Board of Canada, 1951; 1966 (Box 134)
  - National Foreign Policy Conference for Non-Governmental Organizations, See also New York State Education Department (NYSED). (Box 134)
  - National Institute of Adult Continuing Education (NIACE)
    - Correspondence, 1983; 1986,; 1991,; 1994-1995,; 2003,; 2010 (Box 134)
    - Printed material, 1993-1995; 2008,; undated; publication catalog, annual report, project brochures, "An adult higher education: A vision" policy paper, etc. (Box 134)
  - National Institute of Adult Education (NIAE), 1980-1981; publication catalog, informational brochure (Box 134)
  - National Institute for Literacy, 1994; 1997-1998,; 2000-2001; 2 folders; program information, printed material (Box 134)
  - National Seminar for University Administrators, 1959; 1964; AEA project proposal (Box 134)
  - National Society for the Study of Education, 1953; 1957 (Box 134)
  - National Swedish Board of Universities and Colleges, 1978; newsletters (Box 134)
  - National University Continuing Education Association (NUCEA)
    This organization has had several names. See also National University Extension Association (NUEA), which was the name of the organization from 1915 to 1980; National University Continuing Education Association (NUCEA), which was its name from 1980 to 1996; University Continuing Education Association (UCEA), which was its name from 1996 to 2011; and University Professional and Continuing Education Association (UPCEA), which is its current name.
    - Awards and Honors, 1974-1975; booklet; may have been associated with annual conferences (Box 134)
    - Conferences, much of this material consists only of attendee/registration lists
      - Annual Conference, 70th, 1985 (Box 134)
      - Annual Conference, 72d, 1987; banquet program only (Box 134)
      - Annual Conference, 76th, 1991 (Box 134)
      - Annual Conference, 78th, 1993 (Box 134)
      - Annual Conference, 79th, 1994 (Box 134)
      - Annual Conference, 80th, 1995 (Box 135)
      - Annual Conference, 81st, 1996 (Box 135)
      - Region II Conference, 1982 (Box 135)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1996 (Box 135)
    - Handbook for Professional Development in Continuing Higher Education, 1990 (Box 135)
    - Institutional Leadership Project proposal, 1983; proposal to Kellogg Foundation (Box 135)
    - Interview with Alexander Charters, 1988-1989; interviewed by Frank Funk; 2 copies plus release form (Box 135)
    - Membership directory, 1988 (Box 135)
    - Newsletters, 1987-1996; some gaps in coverage (Box 135)
    - Oral history project proposal, "Structured Interviews with Senior Leaders of NUCEA", 1985 (Box 135)
    - Past presidents, several lists, most recent covers 1916-1996; brief bios; "favorite NUEA/NUCEA experiences" collected at 1985 annual conference (Box 135)
    - Printed material, miscellaneous, brochures, occasional paper, subcommittee newsletters, etc. (Box 135)
    - Professional Development Committee report, 1975 (Box 136)
  - National University Extension Association (NUEA)
    - Administrative manual, 1965-1966 (Box 136)
    - Articles of incorporation, 1919; circa 1960; photocopy of 1919 originals; undated later revision (Box 136)
    - Board of Directors minutes, 1961-1967; 2 folders; gaps in coverage (Box 136)
    - Bylaws, 1964; undated (Box 136)
    - Charters' recollections, undated; typescript of Charters' recollections of his relationship with NUCEA (Box 136)
    - Conferences, some conferences are better represented than others; some contain only programs and registration lists, others include committee reports, positions papers, resolutions, etc.
      - List of annual meetings, covers 1915-1966, with location and host institution (Box 136)
      - Annual meeting, 32nd, 1947 (Box 136)
      - Annual meeting, 33rd, 1948 (Box 136)
      - Annual meeting, 35th, 1950 (Box 136)
      - Annual meeting, 36th, 1951 (Box 136)
      - Annual meeting, 37th, 1952 (Box 136)
      - Annual meeting, 39th, 1954 (Box 136)
      - Annual meeting, 40th, 1955 (Box 136)
      - Annual meeting, 41st, 1956 (Box 136)
      - Annual meeting, 42nd, 1957 (Box 136)
      - Annual meeting, 43rd, 1958 (Box 137)
      - Annual meeting, 44th, 1959 (Box 137)
      - Annual meeting, 45th, 1960 (Box 137)
      - Annual meeting, 46th, 1961 (Box 137)
      - Annual meeting, 47th, 1962 (Box 137)
      - Annual meeting, 48th, 1963 (Box 137)
      - Annual meeting, 49th, 1964 (Box 137)
      - Annual meeting, 50th, 1965 (Box 137)
      - Annual meeting, 51st, 1966; includes packet from Association for Field Services in Teacher Education conference, May 1964 (Box 137)
      - Annual meeting, 51st, 1966; proceedings (Box 138)
      - Annual meeting, 52nd, 1967 (Box 138)
      - Annual meeting, 59th, 1974 (Box 138)
      - Annual meeting, 60th, 1975 (Box 138)
      - Annual meeting, 63rd, 1978 (Box 138)
      - Annual meeting, 64th, 1979 (Box 138)
      - Annual meeting, 65th, 1980 (Box 138)
    - Constitution, 1950; 1958,; 1960,; 1964 (Box 138)
    - Continuing Education for Educators of Adults (CEEA), 1974-1976; 2 folders; unclear if this was a committee or project or some other type of effort; correspondence includes many other adult education organizations such as CAEO. (Box 138)
    - Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 138)
    - Correspondence, 1953-1963; 9 folders (Box 139)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1965 Aug; 6 folders (Box 140)
    - Correspondence, 1965 Sep-1966; 5 folders (Box 141)
    - Correspondence, 1967-1981; undated; 8 folders (Box 142)
    - Deans and directors, 1959-1964; also includes scattered lists of committee heads, division heads, etc. (Box 142)
    - Directories, 1965-1966 (Box 142)
    - Division of Evening Colleges and Class Extension, 1954-1957; 3 folders (Box 142)
    - Division of Evening Colleges and Class Extension, 1965; undated (Box 143)
    - Executive Committee minutes, 1955-1956; 1966-1967,; undated (Box 143)
    - "Expanding Horizons...Continuing Education" Golden Anniversary publication, 1965; hardbound volume published on 50th anniversary of NUEA (Box 143)
    - Handbook of Organization, 1961 (Box 143)
    - History of NUEA, 1964 (Box 143)
    - Newsletters
      - NUEA Bulletin, 1948-1956 (Box 143)
      - NUEA Spectator, 1956-1958; 1965,; 1971; photocopied title page only for 1971 issue (Box 143)
      - Miscellaneous, 1970s-1980s (Box 143)
    - Nolte Award, 1965-1966; 2004; includes press release about ANC receiving it and nomination packet from Tom Kowalik; See also University Continuing Education Association: Awards; Memorabilia: Awards and certificates, 2004. (Box 143)
    - Past presidents, 1975-1982; includes Charters' recollections, list of past presidents, (Box 143)
    - Printed material, miscellaneous, 2 folders; informational brochures about NUEA, photocopied title page from 1971 issue of "The Spectator," booklets published by NUEA; etc. (Box 143)
    - Professional Development Committee report, undated (Box 144)
    - Project Head Start
      - Correspondence and notes, 1964-1966; 3 folders; includes Office of Economic Opportunity, University of Maryland, etc. (Box 144)
      - Conference for participating institutions, 1965 (Box 144)
      - Curriculum and schedule, [1965] (Box 144)
      - Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO) contract, 1965 (Box 144)
      - Staff training program, 1965 (Box 144)
    - Reports, papers, proposals, etc., Some are by individuals, some by NUEA committees, others by the NUEA as a whole; all are typescript, some with corrections.; For published reports, see National University Extension Association (NUEA): Printed material, miscellaneous. Additional reports may be found in some of the conference folders.
      - A-F (Box 144)
        American Foreign Policy Seminars (grant application); AUEC-NUEA: Merger or cooperation? by Richard T. Deters (article, undated); The basis of continuing education (article draft, undated); Correspondence study in child development centers (proposal, 1965?); Criteria and standards of the division of correspondence study (white paper, 1962); Education and training for the drug industry at American universities and colleges, by Robert Pitchell (paper, 1968?); Financial assistance to adults in continuing higher education classes by Alan Knox (research prospectus, 1964)
      - P (Box 145)
        Planning for neighborhood programs, by Len Duhl (working paper, 1965); Position paper of NUEA (several drafts and final, 1961); Preliminary draft of a request for a grant to finance a study of correspondence education (grant application, 1963); Proposal for extending technical assistance for extension programs in institutions of higher education, by Robert Pitchell (draft and final, 1966)
      - S (Box 145)
        State legislation affecting higher education in the South (1953); Statements before the Special Subcommittee on Education (4 items, 1965); Study of NUEA independent study programs and administrators, by Elizabeth Powell (1974); Summary and recommendations on the reauthorization of the higher education act (1991); Survey of the current situation in higher adult education in the United States: Research, problems and issues, by Robert Pitchell (undated)
      - U-W (Box 145)
        University of Wisconsin experiments in correspondence study (1955); Workable plan for the community, by S. Zisman (1960); Workers' education (1924)
    - View of the Future committee, 1970-1972; undated; includes reports from the committee (Box 145)
  - National Urban League, See Urban League of Onondaga County.
  - Ndlovu, Sikhanyiso, 1994-1996; 2000,; undated; Deputy Minister for Higher Education, Zimbabwe; See also Zimbabwe Distance Education College (ZDEC). (Box 145)
  - Neff, Monroe, 1967; 1978,; 1989 (Box 145)
  - New Perspectives in University Correspondence Study by Gayle Childs and Charles Wedemeyer, 1958-1964 (Box 145)
  - New Resources Alliance proposal, 1974; proposal to Rockefeller Foundation (Box 145)
  - New York Adult Education Council (NYAEC), 1954-1957; 1968 (Box 145)
  - New York Association for Continuing Education (NYACE), See New York Association for Continuing/Community Education Inc. (NYACCE).
  - New York Association for Continuing/Community Education Inc. (NYACCE)
    - Bylaws, 2005 (Box 145)
    - Conferences, 1975-1979; brochures, programs (Box 145)
    - Correspondence, 1971-1984 (Box 145)
    - Correspondence, 2002-2006 (Box 146)
    - Newsletters, 1975-1980; 2004-2006,; 2009; gaps in coverage (Box 146)
  - New York State Advisory Council on Continuing Higher Education (NYSACCHE), majority of material relates to Title I of the U.S. Higher Education Act
    - Annual report, 9th, 1975 (Box 146)
    - Bylaws, undated (Box 146)
    - Correspondence, 1966; 1971,; 1973,; 1976,; undated; 4 folders (Box 146)
    - Reports, papers, etc., 2 folders (Box 146)
      Ad hoc help in the cities of the nitty gritties, by Charles Bonstead and Alan Hahn (1966); Community service and post secondary continuing education, 1966-1973 (1973); Department position paper on occupational education (1966; 2 copies); Mixed economy to meet higher education needs, by James Hester (1966); New York State teachers reserve: A summary (undated); State plan for community service and continuing higher education programs under Title I of the Higher Education Act of 1963 (1966, 1975); Title I HEA 1965 and continuing education: A proposal for an alternative future, by Robert Williams (1973)
  - New York State Education Department (NYSED)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1967; 1973-1975,; 1981; 3 folders (Box 147)
    - "A new look at continuing education," SUNY-Albany, undated (Box 147)
    - Printed material, miscellaneous, brochures, etc.; topics include college proficiency exams, adult basic education, report from Congressional committee on urban affairs and adult education; directory of services (Box 147)
    - Regents Statewide Plan for the Expansion and Development of Higher Education, 1964 (Box 147)
    - Title I, grant applications from various colleges and universities in New York State, alphabetized by name of school
      - Proposals, A-Col (Box 147)
        Adirondack Community College; Bank Street College of Education; Bronx Community College (CUNY); Columbia University General Studies; Columbia University College of Pharmacy
      - Proposals, Cor-F (Box 147)
        Cornell Cooperative Extension; Cornell University; Dutchess Community College; Fordham University
      - Proposals, H-I (Box 147)
        Hofstra University; Hudson Valley Community College; Hunter College; Immaculata College
      - Proposals, K-Na (Box 148)
        Kingsborough Community College; Mt. St. Mary College; Nassau Community College
      - Proposals, New... (Box 148)
        New School for Social Research; New York Institute of Technology
      - Proposals, New... (Box 148)
        New York State College of Agriculture at Cornell; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell
      - Proposals, NYU-Sa (Box 148)
        New York University; Sarah Lawrence College
      - Proposals, SUNY schools (Box 148)
        Albany, Buffalo, Cobleskill, Delhi, Farmingdale, Morrisville, Potsdam, Stony Brook
      - Proposals, Su-W (Box 148)
        Suffolk County Community College; Syracuse University; Teachers College (Columbia University); University of Rochester; Westchester Community College
      - Regional efforts in postsecondary education in New York State under H.E.A. I: Past, present and future, 1975; remarks delivered at state-wide meeting (Box 148)
      - Submission guidelines, 1967; 1975,; 1976 (Box 148)
      - Miscellany, text of original bill, lists of legislators, Federal Register excerpts, etc. (Box 149)
  - New York State Foundations of Education Association (NYSFEA), 1993-1996; includes constitution, minutes, newsletter, Spring 1995 issue of Educational Change: A journal of role analysis and institutional change (Box 149)
  - Newing, Ralph, 1967 (Box 149)
  - Niemi, John, 1967; 1971,; 1976,; 1979,; 1984,; 1987,; 1992-1993,; 1997-2002,; 2005; includes c.v. (Box 149)
  - Nigeria, general, includes information on visit of Dr. Adesiyan and others to Syracuse; card from Chief Adetunje; card from Mrs. A. N. O. Jaja with photograph; See also World Conference on Comparative Education, Ibadan, Nigeria. (Box 149)
  - Nolte, Julius, See National University Extension Association (NUEA): Nolte award; University Continuing Education Association: Awards; Memorabilia: Awards and certificates, 2004.
  - Non-destructive Academy of South Africa (NASA), undated (Box 149)
  - Non-tax financing of community and continuing education, See Senior educators of adults from England.
  - Normie, Gerald, 1987; 1991,; 1994,; 1996,; undated (Box 149)
    See also Open University.
  - North America, Central America and the Caribbean (NORCECA), 1976; includes photographs of ANC and John Morris at conference (Box 149)
  - North American Alliance for Popular and Adult Education (NAAPAE)
    - Correspondence, 2000-2003; 2008; Larry Olds is main correspondent; includes email issues of "Voices Rising" newsletter as sent by Olds to NAAPAE members (Box 149)
    - Newsletters, 1998-2000; 2008 (Box 149)
  - North American Conference on Adult Education (NACAE), 1960; 1967; most relates to 1960 conference held August 22-31 in Buenos Aires (Box 149)
  - Northwest Adult Education Association (NAEA), 1976; includes brochure with brief history of the organization (Box 149)
  - Northwest Indian College, 1991-1992 (Box 149)
  - Nova University/ Nova Southeastern University, 1993-1994; 2003-2004; Ed.D. degree catalog, miscellaneous printed material, announcements for two issues of "New horizons in adult education" including editor's preface (Box 149)
  - Novicke, 1998-2001; scattered issues; information on Lifelong Learning Week (Box 150)
    See also Slovene Adult Education Center.
  - Nwokafor, Jonathan, undated; dissertation proposal, "A study of the problems in Nigerian education and in specified areas of administration as perceived by Nigerian college students in the state of New York" (Box 150)
  - N, miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 150)
  - Obanewa, Olaitan, 1976; 1979,; 1981-1983,; 1989-1990,; 1994,; 1997; SU doctoral student from Nigeria (Box 150)
  - Odokara, E. O., 1966; 1977-1978; includes text of his speech for National Literacy Day 1977 (Box 150)
    See also World Conference on Comparative Education, Ibadan, Nigeria: Papers, J-O.
  - Ohio State University, 1957; 1973,; 1975,; 1994; also includes photocopies of items dating from 1928-1969; faculty evaluations and clippings relating to Andrew Hendrickson and Herschel Nisonger; bibliography by John Ohliger for required course on adult/continuing education (Box 150)
  - Ohliger, John, 1971; 1974-1983,; 1987-1994,; 1999,; undated; 3 folders; includes lots of material relating to Basic Choices Inc. as well as "My search for freedom's song: Notes for a memoir" (Box 150)
    See also Ohio State University.
  - Okamura, Seiichi, 1960; 1964-1966,; 1972; Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology (Box 150)
  - Okedara, Joseph T., 1971; 1990-1995; University of Ibadan, Nigeria (Box 150)
  - Olds, Larry, See North American Alliance for Popular and Adult Education (NAAPAE); International Council for Adult Education (ICAE).
  - Oliver, Leonard, 1979; 1983,; 1988,; 1991; includes c.v. (Box 150)
  - Omnibus film collection, 1961; 1975-1976,; 1984 (Box 150)
    See Syracuse University: Library: Omnibus donation.
  - Onondaga Citizens League, 1982; 1985,; 1989,; 2000,; 2012; majority relates to 1985 study topic on revising the city and county charters (Box 150)
  - Onondaga County Bicentennial Planning, 1975 (Box 151)
  - Onondaga Historical Association (OHA), 1989-1993; 1998,; 2002-2003,; 2013; includes "Portraits of the Past" no's 1, 2 and 3 (Box 151)
    See also Adult Education in Onondaga County.
  - Ontario Institute for Studies in Education (OISE), 1968; 1973-1980,; 1990,; 1995; includes substantial material on dissertation of Carol Mallette (Box 151)
  - Onushkin, Victor, 1983; 1987,; 1990,; 1992 (Box 151)
  - Open University
    - Correspondence, 1981-1989; 1993-1994; most is with Gerald Normie; also includes some newsletters (Box 151)
    - Printed material, 1993-1995; 2 folders; course catalogs, degree and application information, sample course material (Box 151)
  - Oral History Project
    See also Syracuse University: Center for the Study of Adult Education (CSAE).
    - Correspondence and notes (Box 151)
    - Proposal, 2 folders; proposal to National Endowment for the Humanities; draft and final (Box 151)
  - Oregon State University, 1953; 1990 (Box 151)
  - Orgalime, See Groenhart, Nicholas.
  - Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), 1974; 1977 (Box 152)
  - Osman, John, 1974; 1977-1978,; 1984,; 1987,; 1990; includes biographical sketch (Box 152)
  - Overseas Education Fund, League of Women Voters, 1963-1965; 5-year coordinated plan for action in Central America (Box 152)
  - Oxenham, John, 1998; Including the 900 million plus draft outline (Box 152)
  - Oxford University, 1972-1973; regarding joint course (Box 152)
    See also Coles, Edwin K. Townsend; Jessup, Frank.
  - O, miscellaneous (Box 152)
  - Pakistani Administrative Staff College, 1963; descriptive booklet (Box 152)
  - Pan-European Conference on Adult Education, Barcelona, 1996; See UNESCO: Conferences: Pan-European Conference on Adult Education, Barcelona.
  - Pardoen, Alan R., 1976-1979; relates to Pardoen's co-authoring of chapter on legislation in "Handbook of Adult Education" (Box 152)
  - Parjanen, Matti, 1992-1993; includes review by ANC of Parjanen's book, Legitimation in Adult Education, for International Review of Education (Box 152)
  - Partners of the Americas, CNY/Trinidad-Tobago Chapter
    - Bylaws, constitution (Box 152)
    - Correspondence, 1978-1988; 1995-1996,; undated; 3 folders (Box 152)
    - Minutes, 1982-1984; 1986-1988; Executive Committee, Board of Directors (Box 152)
    - Printed material, 2 folders; annual reports, newsletters, forms, photocopies of clippings, etc. (Box 152)
  - Pastrana, Andres, 1994-1995; includes statement by ANC, "Project on andragogy at Simon Rodriguez University" (Box 153)
  - Patek, Jaroslav, 1987 (Box 153)
  - Peace Corps Training
    - Correspondence, 1965-1967; 2 folders; cooperative project with Syracuse University (Box 153)
    - Final report, 1966; 2 folders (Box 153)
    - Proposal, includes paper by Iversen, "The Peace Corps challenge to higher education" (Box 153)
  - Pemberton, Clive, 1986-1987; University of Nottingham; includes "Pilgrim College Report" and "Fighting the cuts: Success in a small town" (Box 153)
  - Pennsylvania Association for Adult and Continuing Education (PAACE), 1991-1992; includes draft and published version of article by ANC, "Adult Education: 21st Century" published in PAACE journal (Box 153)
  - Pennsylvania State University, 1957; 1984,; 1993-1994; distance education; course brochure (Box 153)
  - People to People, See Soviet Union / China trip; Memorabilia: Photographs, personal: China and Russia.
  - Peru, general, Campos (Box 153)
  - Phelan, Tom, 1992; 1995-2007,; 2010-2012,; undated; includes a few papers by Phelan and some printed material for his company, Strategic Teaching Associates, Inc. (Box 153)
  - Phi Delta Kappa, includes national and Syracuse University Chapter
    - Correspondence, 1973-1975; 1978-1980,; 1992-1997,; 2001-2003,; 2006; mass mailings to PDK members (Box 153)
    - Memorabilia, 1982; 1996; includes certificate of recognition for service (Box 154)
    - Publications, 1979-1981; 1991-1998; newsletters (Box 154)
  - Philippines, 1967; 1976 (Box 154)
  - Physical Education, Canada, 1941-1942; 1949; pertains to ANC's application for High School Physical Education Certificate (Box 154)
  - Pierce, William A, 1978-1979; includes photocopies of earlier items, including writings by Pierce, going back to 1951 (Box 154)
  - Pirkl, James, 1965-1983 (Box 154)
  - Pitchell, Robert J., 1971; 1973,; 1976-1977 (Box 154)
  - Pitonzo, Linda, 2001-2002; 2005 (Box 154)
  - Planned Parenthood Federation of America, 1969; See World Education: Literacy and family planning conference, Syracuse.
  - Pöggeler, Franz, 1987-1992; 1996-1997,; 2002,; 2009; includes two papers by Pöggeler, "History of adult education as history of adult educators" and "The state and adult education" (Box 154)